בוקר טוב. Boker tov. All right, today's דף daf is י"ג. Yud
Gimmel. We
had done the משנה Mishnah yesterday, but you know, I knew this
was going to happen. I figured like, all right, we can't just
start without גמרא. Gemara. So we're going to reread the
משנה, Mishnah, which raises questions why we read it the last two
minutes of yesterday. But okay, let's pick up with the משנה Mishnah
at the bottom of י"ב עמוד ב'. Yud Bais Amud Bais. הריני
נזיר לכשיהיה לי בן, Hareini nazir l'shichyei li ben, I'll be a
נזיר nazir if I have a son. ונולד לו בן, V'nolad lo
ben, and he has a son, הרי זה נזיר, harey zeh nazir,
you're a נזיר. nazir. נולד לו בת טומטום ואנדרוגינוס, Nolad lo bas,
tumtum, v'androgynous,
if it was a daughter, a טומטום tumtum or an אנדרוגינוס. androgynous.
טומטום Tumtum is a person whose genitalia is covered up, he's male
or female, you don't know which one. He's male or she's female.
And אנדרוגינוס androgynous is with both genitalia. So that's a question of
halakhically how do we categorize such a person? So אינו נזיר, eino
nazir, not a נזיר. nazir. So presumably the חידוש chiddush here would
be that טומטום tumtum is you don't say that that's a ספק,
saffek, that when he says a בן, ben, he means a בן
ודאי. ben vadai. אם אמר לכשיהיה לי ולד, Im amar l'shichyei li
v'lad, if he says when I have a child, אפילו נולד לו
בת טומטום ואנדרוגינוס, afilu nolad lo bas, tumtum, v'androgynous, הרי זה נזיר.
harey zeh nazir. Even if it's non-male, if it's a daughter or
a טומטום tumtum and אנדרוגינוס, androgynous, you're a נזיר, nazir, not much
of a חידוש chiddush there. הפילה אשתו אינו נזיר, Hipilah ishto eino
nazir, if his wife miscarried, he's not a נזיר. nazir. And here
the assumption in the משנה Mishnah seems to be, and I maybe
said this a little quickly yesterday, that if his wife miscarried a
child that was considered viable, you know, כלו לו חדשיו, kalu lo
chodashav, that he had had already a full term and it was
considered to be viable, then even though he was not born alive,
presumably if the child had been viable and then miscarried, that actually
would have fallen into the category of לכשיהיה לי ולד. l'shichyei li
v'lad. I don't know why that's the assumption, that seems to be
the assumption. You could say that's actually the point of the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma that it's not in that category, but the גמרא
Gemara is going to assume that the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma would
concede that it would be in that category, but that the only
point of the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is you don't know if
the child was viable or not. So that gets to the old
question of what do you do if somebody makes נזירות nezirus on
a condition and you don't know if the condition is met? And
the גמרא Gemara is going to say that the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma assumes that if there's a ספק saffek if that condition is
met, this is the position of רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, that לא
נחית איניש נפשיה לספיקא, lo nachis inish nafshai l'safeka,
that a person basically means when they make a condition, maybe specifically
by נזיר, nazir, whatever, that unless the condition is definitely met, it's
not met. Okay, so therefore the person is not a נזיר. nazir.
If it was really early on, everyone would agree he's not a
נזיר. nazir.
Right. Everyone would,
if it really was viable, everybody would agree he is a נזיר.
nazir.
No, I'm saying if it was early on, it wouldn't have been
viable.
If it was early on, then everybody presumably would agree it's not.
Dead ולד v'lad is not a ולד v'lad for the purposes of
נזירות, nezirus, right? In other words...
No, but again, it is for the purposes of let's say טומאת
לידה, tumat leidah, that would even be after forty days. So you
know, it's an interesting question what you define as נולד. nolad. But
you're right, there's a difference between an act of לידה leidah and
whether the child is considered to be a בן ben or ולד
v'lad and so on. רבי שמעון אומר יאמר, Rabbi Shimon omer yomar,
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says no, it's a ספק. saffek. So therefore
he's a ספק נזיר. saffek nazir. Now, being a ספק נזיר saffek
nazir is the worst of both worlds. You have to practice נזירות,
nezirus, but you have no way of ending it. Because if you're
not a נזיר, nazir, you can't bring the קרבנות. korbanot. If you
are a נזיר, nazir, you have to bring the קרבנות korbanot to
end it. So the only way you get out of being a
ספק נזיר saffek nazir is you make yourself into a ודאי נזיר.
vadai nazir. And here's what you do. יאמר, Yomar, אם היה בן
קיימא, im haya ben kayama, הריני נזיר חובה. hareini nazir chovah. The
person should stipulate and say, look, if that child was viable, you
know, potentially viable until it was miscarried, then right now I'll do
נזירות, nezirus, the נזירות nezirus that I'm obligated to be because of
my earlier condition. ואם לאו, V'im lav, but if that was not
a viable child, so I don't have an obligatory נזירות nezirus on
me right now, הריני נזיר נדבה, hareini nazir nedavah, I accept upon
myself now a freewill נזירות. nezirus. So one way or the other,
either because I'm a נזיר nazir because that was considered a child,
and if that were not true, then I'm a נזיר nazir because
right now I'm accepting נזירות. nezirus. Fine. חזרה וילדה, Chazra v'yaldah, now
his wife had a second child. Okay, so according to the תנא
קמא, Tanna Kamma, the first ספק saffek did not count as a
satisfying of the תנאי. t'nai. So now the תנאי t'nai is satisfied.
So הרי זה נזיר, harey zeh nazir, you are a נזיר. nazir.
Now according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, you don't know. Because it
could be the first child was not viable and the first נזירות
nezirus you did was
freewill. And now your real condition was met and you're obligated to
do a real נזירות. nezirus. That's one scenario. The other scenario is
you did your obligatory נזירות nezirus earlier and you don't have an
obligation now. So you're once again in this area of ספק נזיר.
saffek nazir. So again you have to solve it the same way.
So רבי שמעון אומר יאמר, Rabbi Shimon omer yomar, you should say,
אם הראשון בן קיימא, im harishon ben kayama, if the first one
was viable and therefore that was my obligatory נזירות, nezirus, הראשון חובה,
harishon chovah, the first נזירות nezirus I practiced already was my obligatory
one, וזו נדבה, v'zo nedavah, now I accept a freewill one. ואם
לאו, V'im lav, and if the first one was not viable, so
what I did back then was just a new נזירות, nezirus, הראשון
נדבה, harishon nedavah, then the first one was a new freely accepted
נזירות, nezirus, וזו חובה, v'zo chovah, and this is my obligatory one.
Okay, so for each child, for each time, you have a ספק
נזיר saffek nazir and the way you solve it is you turn
it into a ודאי נזיר. vadai nazir. Okay, let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. האי מאי למימרא? Hai mai l'memra? So going
on the first line of the משנה, Mishnah, he says if I
have a son, he has a son, he's a נזיר. Nazir. Of
course, what else, what else would I think? No, משום סיפא. mishum
seifa. It's the חידוש chiddush is the second part. בת טומטום ואנדרוגינוס
אינו נזיר. Bat, tumtum, v'androgynus eino nazir. If he's a daughter, a
טומטום, tumtum, if he, if a child is a daughter, a טומטום,
tumtum, אנדרוגינוס, androgynus, then the person is not a נזיר. Nazir. פשיטא,
Pshita, that's obvious. You said בן. ben. Now I don't think it's
obvious, טומטום tumtum might be a בן, ben, just you don't know.
But let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. מהו דתימא לכשאבנה
הוא דקאמר, Mahu d'teima l'chsh'ebaneh hu d'ka'amar, maybe when he says יהא
לי בן, yehei li ben, בן ben doesn't mean a son, בן
ben means something that I will be built by, and it means
a child. Okay, but it's a ולד, v'lad, or a זרע, zera,
or something like that.
Right, that seems like a bad answer.
I would have thought that's, I understand, a bad answer to me.
Anyway, קמשמע לן דלא, kamashma lan d'lo, we don't interpret it that
way. בן Ben is son. Okay, there's a lot of other words
that are available. What?
It's a biblical language,
אבנה
ממנה, ibaneh mimena, but to actually call the child a בן, ben,
right, this is, I don't know if you have it. Obviously Hebrew
defaults to the masculine. So if you want to say children, you
can say בנים, banim, right, ובנים אין לו u'banim ein lo or
something like that, you know, or you could say ובן אין לו,
u'ben ein lo, although anyway. But to say יהא לי בן, yehei
li ben, like as a noun,
it's a strange answer. I would have thought the bigger חידוש chiddush
is the טומטום. tumtum. טומטום Tumtum is a ספק, safek, is either
a son or daughter, you just don't know which one. So, you
know, now maybe it's, maybe again, we're going to תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma that says if you're a ספק נזיר, safek nazir, not a
נזיר. nazir. But who knows what happens if a year later, the
טומטום, tumtum, the thing that's covering up, the skin that's covering up
the genitalia is removed and it's discovered that he is a boy.
Right? So what do you say? Then you say retroactively you are
a נזיר, Nazir, not a נזיר. Nazir. That's an interesting question, right?
So to me the טומטום tumtum is the interesting question. Anyway, but
the גמרא Gemara does not answer that. So it does not go
there. Okay, ואם אמר שיהיה לי ולד, v'im amar she'yehei li v'lad,
if you say if I have a child,
then a son, daughter, טומטום, tumtum, אנדרוגינוס, androgynus, you're a נזיר. Nazir.
So the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא, pshita, that's also obvious. No, מהו
דתימא ולד דמיחשב בעיני אינשי בעינן. mahu d'teima v'lad d'michshav beinei inshi
ba'inan. If you say a child, you mean a child that people
see as significant, which means basically a son, as opposed to a
daughter. So where are all of the women in our דף daf
right now? We need somebody playing the role of רבקה Rivka to
give me a hard time right now, but you know, this is
the גמרא, Gemara, you know. I mean, the sad reality is that
this is true even till today. You know, when people are able
to, you know, besides China, where there's all that, right, where basically
what, they leave their daughters to die so that they can have
sons. India too. What? India too.
India too. Although there are selective abortions.
But when people are able to also select the, use, you know,
modern technology to select the sex of the child, you know, overwhelmingly
people choose to have boys rather than girls.
I mean, I think not in the United
States.
Really? Yes. Girls are preferred. Really? I did not know that. But
look, anyway, partly this reflects a societal reality that men have it
easier in society than women, you know. Anyway, so I might think
that even if you say ולד v'lad in the generic, you mean
a son, קמשמע לן, kamashma lan, no, you said a child, so
you mean a child.
So what would you have said if you meant a?
I don't know. You're right, I don't know. Okay, so the גמרא,
Gemara, I understand, it's just to explain what the, why it was
needed.
You could have said, the בבלי Bavli can't take everything you say
and what it sounds like.
No, because then it's too transparently obvious, so you need to have
a little bit of a חידוש. chiddush. Okay, הפילה אשתו אינו נזיר.
hipila ishto eino nazir. Now we get to what's the real חידוש
chiddush of the משנה Mishnah which is the end, if his wife
miscarries he's not a נזיר. Nazir.
מאן תני לה, man t'ni la, who teaches this? רבי יהודה דקרי
הוא, Rabbi Yehuda d'kri hu, or דקרי. d'keri. It's רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda about the pile. You might remember, the guy says I'm a
נזיר Nazir if when we go to
my threshing floor we find in that pile of wheat a hundred
כור. kor. And then they go and they find that the whole
pile had been stolen. So there's no way of knowing, was it
there or not there, was the condition met or not met? So
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says אינו נזיר. eino nazir. And the way
the גמרא Gemara explains his position is that basically if you, when
you say a condition and you don't know if it's met, you
never would have wanted to be a נזיר ספק nazir safek because
that's worse than even being a נזיר ודאי nazir vadai as we've
seen. So therefore, you only meant that the condition should take effect
if it was definite, right, if there was any, if it was
doubtful, then you never wanted the נזירות nezirut to take effect. The
נזירות nezirut would only take effect if the condition was definitely met.
לא נחית איניש נפשיה לספיקא. lo nachis inish nafshay l'sefeika. So here
too, even though if the child were considered to be viable when
it was miscarried, to have been viable, then you would be a
נזיר Nazir if we knew that for sure, but if we don't
know that for sure, you're definitely not a נזיר. Nazir. You're not
a ספק נזיר. safek nazir. That's רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position. רבי
שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon Omer, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you are
a ספק נזיר safek nazir and you have to deal with it.
יאמר Yomar you should say,
אם היה בן קיימא הריני נזיר חובה ואם לאו הריני נזיר נדבה.
im hayah ben kayama hareni nazir chova, v'im lav hareni nazir nedava.
And you make a condition, if that was viable, the miscarried baby,
then I am a נזיר Nazir through that original vow and if
not, I'm accepting נזירות nezirut now. In one way or the other,
you're a definite נזיר Nazir now, you bring your קרבנות korbanot and
you'll be done. בעי מיניה רבי אבא מרב הונא. ba'i minei Rabbi
Abba mi'Rav Huna. בעי מיניה רב אבא מרב הונא. ba'ei minei Rav
Abba meRav Huna. רב אבא Rav Abba asked רב הונא: Rav Huna:
הריני נזיר לכשיהיה לי בן. hareini nazir l'kesheyihye li ben. והפילה אשתו.
vehipila ishto. A guy says, I'll be a נזיר nazir if I
have a son, just like the משנה, mishnah, and his wife miscarried,
just like the משנה. mishnah. Now we're going to say in a
minute we're dealing with רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, okay, so his wife
miscarried, he's definitely not a נזיר, nazir, fine. Then what happens? והפריש
קרבן, vehifrish korban, he separated out a קרבן korban because I don't
know, he felt well who knows, maybe it was a בן, ben,
maybe it was a ולד, vlad, it doesn't mean בן ben or
ולד. vlad. Anyway, he separates out a קרבן. korban. וחזרה וילדה, vechozra
veyalda, and then apparently it was
without getting pregnant again, right, she went ahead, she had twins, and
she went ahead and then she gave birth to a live second
child. Okay, so מה? mah? Like three seconds later?
Yeah,
I mean within three nine seconds he was מקדיש makdish
an animal right next to him. Basically, I don't know, you and
I are saying seconds because we can't imagine any other scenario. Whether
the גמרא gemara could have imagined that like a month later, I
don't know what the גמרא gemara is imagining. Let's okay, but anyway,
let's for us say a few seconds later. Okay, so the question
now is, he sanctified the animal after the first child. Now that
he's got a second living child, he obviously has to be a
נזיר. nazir. Okay, but that's right, because if the first one wasn't,
the second one his condition was made, he has to be a
נזיר. nazir. But the question is, was he a נזיר nazir from
the time of the first
child? Because if he was only a נזיר nazir from the time
of the second, the animal wouldn't be sanctified. The animal's only sanctified
if you can be מקדיש makdish it as a קרבן נזיר, korban
nazir, which you can't do if you're not a נזיר. nazir. Okay,
so the question is, we know you're a נזיר, nazir, buddy, but
what we want to know is, were you a נזיר nazir from
the first child? What's the נפקא מינה? nafka mina? The נפקא מינה
nafka mina is whether this קרבן korban is already sanctified, well okay,
so just sanctify it again plainly. Okay, but let's say you don't
sanctify it again and you want to know you use this, have
you done מעילה, meila, are you you know is it אסור assur
to use this animal if you haven't right? So if you were
a נזיר nazir from child one, then the animal was sanctified. If
you're only a נזיר nazir from child two, then the animal isn't
sanctified. So the question is does the birth of child two, now
why what's the relevance of child two? Isn't this exactly the משנה?
mishnah? You had a first child, it was miscarried, the debate of
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon whether you're a
נזיר. nazir. Ah, the question is, does the birth of child two
as a viable child retroactively make you realize that the first child
was viable? You couldn't have had your wife couldn't have had was,
I mean obviously he's dead now, it was a miscarriage, but it
was viable until he died, right? It was considered viable before he
died, before the miscarriage, what?
At least he was viable until he died. Right. No.
Ah. All of us who are living right now are going to
be viable until we die, right? So if the child was considered
to be viable until the actual until the miscarriage, okay, so then
and maybe we can infer that because the twin was viable. What
would one stay and one go to the other? Well, because the
basic assumption of viable or not, you're right, like you could say
who knows, maybe the first one had a heart defect or something,
right, but the basic assumption of viability here is just a question
of how developed the child has been. Did he get to a
stage that he was fully developed? Okay, so maybe that's the better
word to use, כלו לו חדשיו. kalu lo chadashav. So could we
say that since the second one was born living and clearly fully
developed, from that we can learn out that definitely the twin was
also in the same state? So now we find out retroactively that
that child actually was considered fully developed and you were a נזיר
nazir from the first child and therefore the animal is sanctified. That's
the question.
Okay, so when we have a miscarriage, right, we would say it's
a stillbirth.
Stillbirth, yes, thank you,
actually, you know that takes it out. Yeah, you're right and actually
actually that's actually the different terms. A miscarriage where the child was
not considered כלו לו חדשיו kalu lo chadashav would be נפל. nefel.
So she repeats for both הפילה? hepila? No,
I you know, I don't know, I mean you're right.
If it's a נפל, nefel, it's like a stillbirth but really the
situation the reality sounds like it's a stillbirth. Right, it's like being
נולד מת.
nolad met. I mean that's the question, the question is, right,
I think somebody even says this about the language, about whether it's
considered a נפל nefel or ולד. vlad. So if you want, you
could say you know that's the question, is what happened הפלה hapala
and the child a נפל nefel and a miscarriage and
therefore not viable?
Or is it and therefore right, or is it basically like a
stillbirth and it's basically a case of like נולד מת? nolad met?
Okay, so you know and that's like I think helpful exactly that
right to explore that anyway. But whether it was like נפל nefel
versus נולד מת. nolad met. Okay, so that's the question. So we
use the word הפילה hepila because we don't know, but that's exactly
the question. All right, so let's just see, let's just read a
little bit to get the question down and then take the questions
you have. So it says like this, מהו? mahu? Okay, והפריש קרבן
וחזרה וילדה
מהו. vehifrish korban vechozra veyalda mahu.
What do we say? אליבא דמאן, aliba d'man, according to whom? אי
אליבא דרבי שמעון. ei aliba d'Rabbi Shimon. מאי תיבעי tibei, ליה *mai
tivaye lei*. According to Rabbi Shimon, what's your question? הא רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon, ספק safek. נזירות nezirus, להחמיר *ha Rabbi Shimon safek nezirut
lehachmir*. We already know that from the first child, the guy was
a ספק נזיר nazir, *safek nazir*. Okay. So now you could say,
well maybe this would retroactively make us realize that the child was
of, that you were a ודאי *vadai* נזיר nazir *nazir* from the
first child, right? Maybe that's the question. From the fact that there
was a second child, maybe retroactively you say ודאי *vadai*. So תוספות
Tosafos *Tosafot* says from the fact that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
there's no question according to Rabbi Shimon shows that the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is not going to go so far to assume because of
the second child was born living, that would be enough to say
that the first child was
ודאי *vadai*
fully developed. But what we do want, that maybe I don't know
why, we can't say that, staying over different times, maybe?
I don't know, right.
But maybe what it is, but no, but with it's all two
births from the same pregnancy. There's you're about, yeah, I mean otherwise
it would be crazy.
Did they have the case of like the
חייא *Chiya* twins or something like that? Yeah, so maybe to right,
meaning the whether, so that's what's not spelled out, same pregnancy, but
is it three seconds later or three days later or three weeks
later? That I don't know what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is imagining.
Okay, but תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says it's clear from the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* that it's not imagining that somehow the second living child makes
it that the first child would be considered to be ודאי *vadai*
a בן Ben קיימא *ben kayama*, ודאי *vadai* developed. So but what
most are saying could at least let us establish that it was
like ספק בן Ben, קיימא *safek ben kayama*, okay, at least enough.
So according to Rabbi Shimon we don't need that, he's already a
ספק בן ben קיימא *safek ben kayama* and already the guy's a
ספק נזיר nazir? *safek nazir*. So אליבא דמאן *aliba deman*, אי אליבא
דרבי שמעון Shimon *i aliba deRabbi Shimon*, מאי תיבעי tibei. ליה *mai
tivaye lei*. הא רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon. ספק נזירות nezirus. להחמיר *ha
Rabbi Shimon safek nezirut lehachmir*. אלא אליבא דרבי יהודה Yehuda *ela aliba
deRabbi Yehuda*, according to Rabbi Yehuda, דאמר ספק נזירות nezirus להקל *damar
safek nezirut lehakeil*, normally if there's a doubt we just say okay,
it's a doubt, so you're not a נזיר nazir, *nazir* out of
doubt. That's what we would normally say. מאי *mai*, what would we
say here? Here now it's funny, because if Rabbi Yehuda really has
a principled position that any doubt you're not a נזיר nazir. *nazir*,
then it doesn't matter that there's more evidence to bring. As long
as you're not telling me it's 100 percent, you're not a נזיר
nazir *nazir*. So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* is somehow understanding some interesting
middle position here like there's enough evidence that shows that the first
child's really was a בן ben קיימא *ben kayama* that that should
get over Rabbi Yehuda's idea that you can't be a ספק נזיר
nazir *safek nazir*. Maybe it's not 100 percent, so we won't say
I don't know that you would let's say you'd be חייב מעילה
*chayav me'ila* if you misused the קרבן Korban, *korban*, but it's certainly
enough to say
that the laws should take effect. So do we say that second
child is enough to establish that the first child was a בן
ben קיימא *ben kayama* and that you would be considered to have
been a נזיר nazir *nazir* or at least a ספק נזיר nazir?
*safek nazir* even according to Rabbi Yehuda? That's the question. מאי תיבעי
ליה *mai tivaye lei*, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אלא אליבא
דרבי יהודה *ela aliba deRabbi Yehuda*, דאמר ספק נזירות Nezirut להקל *damar
safek nezirut lehakeil*, מהו Mahu? *mahu*, קדוש או לא o lo, קדוש
*kadosh o lo kadosh*, is the first animal sanctified or not? מאי
נפקא מינה *mai nafka mina*, what difference would it make? לגיזתו ולעבודה
בו *legizato ula'avoda bo*, would you be allowed to shear it and
work it? Do you have to assume it's קדוש *kadosh*? Sure, if
you want it sanctified again to be safe or whatever, but you
sanctified another but you don't and you went and you used it
or you want to use it would you be allowed to? What
do you have to assume about the status of the animal? And
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says תיקו teiku, *teiku*, we don't know. So
again it's a strange גמרא gemara. *Gemara* because is it assuming that
the second child was born three minutes later then you would think
like okay ודאי *vadai* that should show you that the first child
was a viable. Now תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says well if they were
fraternal twins and not identical then even if we're assuming you got
let's say the second child was born three minutes later maybe and
it'd be interesting I wish we had a doctor in the room
who could tell us this but maybe,
well you're not that type of doctor. Okay anyway maybe says you
know one egg was fertilized like semen is viable for like three
days, so he says maybe one egg was fertilized like on day
one after intercourse and the next egg was fertilized on day three
after intercourse. Okay. I don't know if that's possible maybe they had
sex again or something like that. So therefore maybe there actually is
like a two day difference between these two fraternal twins in the
womb. That might be possible. I don't know. So he says if
that's possible maybe the second child that was born viable was the
older child right because one of them had been fertilized earlier so
the one that was miscarried even only if it was miscarried five
minutes ago actually was two days younger and therefore had not yet
reached the age and the development of viability.
We're doing it exactly like as to the birth and like the
innate cutoff, yeah whatever it would be.
That's the question. So at least that's like at least okay like
I get that it's a very narrow line but there is some
line. So if you imagine that they're not identical twins maybe there
actually is a few days a two day difference between their age
and maybe that would have been the difference. So that's how תוספות
Tosafot *Tosafot* explains why there's a little bit of a ספק *safek*
here. But somehow the גמרא gemara, *Gemara* assumes that should prove at
least give us a strong sense of confidence that the first child
was definitely viable and maybe that even for Rabbi Yehuda would make
him a נזיר nazir? *nazir*. Now would make him a ודאי נזיר
nazir *vadai nazir* or ספק נזיר nazir *safek nazir*? Rabbi Yehuda is
not supposed to allow for the possibility of a ספק נזיר nazir
*safek nazir* so what type of a middle space you have is
not fully... clear. Yes, Michael?
So according to, I guess, everybody, there's an ענין of בל תאחר
bal te'acher for נזירות, Nezirut. right? Because otherwise, you know, you could
say, alright, just wait, you know, to your next kid.
Yeah, I mean, that's true in the משנה Mishnah according to רבי
שמעון, Shimon why do you have to make a תנאי? tenai? Why
don't you wait? But first of all, who knows? Maybe you'll be
waiting your whole life. It won't necessarily come about. Yeah, that's an
interesting—we had that back in נדרים, Nedarim, whether there was an idea
of בל תאחר bal te'acher by נזירות. Nezirut
The בל תאחר—there's bal te'acher two aspects of that. I'd have to
go double check. One is that you make a נדר neder to
become a נזיר, nazir but you're not a נזיר nazir. now. And
then there's a question of: is there בל תאחר bal te'acher in
actually becoming a נזיר? nosie. Not bringing the קרבנות korbanos of a
נזיר, nosie, but a נדר neder to become, then the becoming is
the satisfying of that vow. That wouldn't be the case here, because
here you said, 'When my wife has a child, I'll be a
נזיר.' nosie She didn't have a child, the condition hasn't been met,
right? So that's not why you have to make the condition for
רבי שמעון. The reason you make the condition is because if you
are a נזיר nosie now, then you want to end it. You
don't want it to go on for 10 years until you're waiting
for your wife to have another child, okay? But there is an
interesting question about
whether—yeah, and how long would it be? I mean, if for קרבנות
korbanos we say three רגלים regalim כסדרן, kesidran, maybe—yeah,
yeah, okay, but that's not immediately relevant here. Here you have to
do it because of whatever. Yeah, because you have a ספק.
Where do you see in תוספות Tosafot the distinction between identical and
fraternal, or טיפה היא נחלקת
לשנים?
tipah
hi necheleket lishnayim?
Yeah, maybe you're right. Maybe I read it through my own lens
to make sense.
טיפה היא נחלקת לשנים, tipah hi necheleket lishnayim, if it means
something
about the twins,
would it
mean
identical twins?
If—if that's what he's talking about at all.
Anyway, they didn't know about the egg.
No, that's the הוה אמינא hava amina that it's definitely is a
ולד קייא. vlad kaya. Okay,
נחלקת לשנים necheleket lishnayim is basically saying that it's identical.
He didn't say what—yeah, I don't know
where—yeah, but if you look three lines down, he says on the
other side, or two lines down at the end of the wide
lines, he says, the תוספות Tosafot 'היא פילא'? hi peilah But two
lines down in the middle-sized lines at the end, he says, דשמא
מקצת הטיפה נקלטה מיד ומקצת הטיפה השניה לא נקלטה עד אחר שני
ימים או ב' ימים. deshema miktzat hatipah nikletah miyad umiktzat hatipah hashniyah
lo nikletah ad achar shney yamim o beis yamim. Okay?
So that's exactly the question. If it was identical, they're the same
age, so the fact that one of them was viable proves that
the other was viable. And if—but maybe they were fraternal, and therefore
they're not the same age. So that's exactly what the question is.
We don't know. If they were identical, we could assume that definitely
it was viable, and if they were fraternal, maybe it wasn't—maybe the
second one wasn't viable, maybe the second one was two days younger
than the first one. Okay. או שמא מקצת... o shema miktzat... yeah,
okay. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara. says like this. So
we left that as a question mark. בעי מיניה בן רחומי מאביי.
ba'i minei ben rechumi me'abaye. בן רחומי, Ben Rechumi, I don't know
where we get him usually, asked from אביי. Abaye. הריני נזיר לכשיהיה
לי בן. harei ani nazir lechisheye li ben. 'I am a נזיר
nosie when I have a child, a son.' ושמע חבירו ואמר ועלי.
veshamah chaveiro ve'amar ve'alai. 'And it should be on me too.'
מה? mah?
What do you mean? אדיבוריה משמע adiburei mashma or אגופיה משמע? agufai
mashma?
Wait, meaning when he has
an—when who has an—whoever says, 'I'm a נזיר nosie when I have
a son,' and שמעון says, 'And and me.' So what does that
mean? When ראובן Reuven has a son, you'll be a נזיר? nosie
Or when you have a son, you'll be a נזיר? nosie Okay?
So, so what does that mean? Okay, מה? mah?
Like, I think you just ask him what he meant.
That's a good question. I mean, you're right, half this מסכת, maseches,
why aren't we asking the guy? Okay, I don't know. או גופיה
משמע. o gufai mashma. אם תמצא לומר גופיה משמע, im timtza lomar
gufai mashma,
if you say 'and on me' means 'and when I have a
son.' אמר הריני נזיר לכשיהיה לי בן ושמע חבירו ואמר ואני, amar
harei ani nazir lechisheye li ben veshamah chaveiro ve'amar ve'ani,
מה? mah? What if he says, rather than he says ועלי, ve'alai,
he says ואני, ve'ani, 'and I'? So you would think the same.
'On me' means, if that means 'when I have a son,' and
'me' means 'when the same thing with me, when I have a
son.' So for some reason ואני ve'ani maybe means something else. מה?
mah? אנפשיה קאמר? anfshiah ka'amar? Does
it mean 'when I have a son' like when you say 'and
on me' it means 'and when I have a son I'll be
a נזיר'? nosie. או דילמא הכי קאמר, o dilma hachi ka'amar, ורחימנא
לך כוותיך. verachimna lach kevaseich.
'I—and you have just told me how much it means to you
to have a son, you'll be a נזיר nosie. when you have
a son, and I, I care for you so much, I care
for you to have a son, I love your son as much
as I love you.' And therefore, like, because I care for you,
I'll also be a נזיר nosie. for—I'll be a נזיר nosie also
if you have a son, I really care for you.
Oh, he's saying ואני ve'ani and I wish you the same?
No, no. ואני ורחימנא לך כוותיך. ve'ani verachimna lach kevaseich.
Something like, I love you as much as I love it or
the son that isn't born or somehow the other thing, I love
your son as much as I love you, and because I care
so much for you, you know, I—it's not saying עלי. alai. If
you say עלי, alai, it's meaning I'm taking an obligation on me.
We step away from you. I'm just saying I'm taking an obligation
on me. What obligation are you taking on me? The obligation I'm
taking myself is if I have a son I'll be a נזיר.
nosie But to say 'and I,' maybe 'and I' is directed towards
'and I care for you.' And I want to help you, and
I want to, you know, not to— and I want to do
the same. Maybe the "I" is directed towards, you know, your relationship
to the other person. And therefore I'm saying, and I also care
for you and if you have a son, I'll also be a
נזיר. nosie Okay, it's a little bit of a חידוש chidush why
עלי Alai and אני Ani would be different. Now interestingly, on the
side there's a different גרסא, girsa, which is the second version is
הריני נזיר לכשיהיה לך בן. Hareini nosie l'ksheyiheye lecha ben. So Michael
said, "I'll be a נזיר, nosie Dov, when you have a son."
And I say, "And me too!"
So now the question is: if what does "me too" mean? "I'll
also be a נזיר nazir when I have a son" or does
"me too" mean "and I'll be a נזיר nazir when you have
a son"? Okay, so that's actually a little bit more in my
mind, a little more interesting than עלי Alai versus אני. Ani. Okay,
so either עלי Alai is a little bit of stepping away from
the guy saying it's אני, Ani, which clearly means when I have
a son or might mean when I have a son, but "and
I" might mean and I am with you here, buddy, buddy, I'm
here, I'm here for you. Okay, and therefore maybe it means when
you have a son.
You see the other גרסא girsa here?
Right here on the right-hand margin. You see where it says ס״א
samech aleph לך? lecha? ספרים אחרים sfarim acherim have לך. lecha. Okay,
or the other version is when you say, when Michael says "when
I have a son" and I say "and me," it means obviously
when I have a son. Everybody, like, you know, אדם קרוב אצל
עצמו. Adam karov eitzel atzmo. So if I'm saying "and me," it
means when I have a son. But if he says "I'll be
a נזיר nazir when you have a son" and I say
"and me," so if we say אדם קרוב אצל עצמו Adam karov
eitzel atzmo then it means "and when I have a son," or
do we say I'm just doing the mirror image of what Michael
did and I mean when Michael has a son? Okay, so those
are interesting questions. Okay, אם תמצא לומר, Im timtza lomar, כה באנפי...
k'vei anpei...
You mean we'll stay with this one? The first person has a
son.
And in which case? לך. lecha.
So who's the לך lecha going on? Me, you, you Michael.
You say "I'll be a נזיר nazir when you, Dov, have a
son" and I say "and me." So the two possibilities: "and me,
I'll be a נזיר nazir when I have a son" or "and
me, and I'll be a נזיר nazir when you, Michael, have a
son." There's only two people here.
Oh, okay, so there's not three? I thought some other Dov?
No, no, no. Oh,
I meant the two of us. All right, let's stop being interesting.
I'm sorry.
If there's another person and says "and me too," you know what?
Essentially the גמרא Gemara doesn't go there. There are two people here.
Okay. All right. So the גמרא says like this, where were we?
אם תמצא לומר, Im timtza lomar, כה באנפי כסיפא ליה מילתא, k'vei
anpei ksifa lei milta,
anytime you're in the presence—you see Michael, I shouldn't say the גמרא
doesn't go there because it's actually about to go there. Okay. Anytime
you're in the presence of the guy who just spoke, you're embarrassed
to somehow
not be...
wait, wait, hold on, let me make sure I got this right.
Hold on, let me make sure I got this right. Hold on.
כה באנפי... k'vei anpei... Hold
on.
Yeah, okay, I was confused for a moment by רש״י Rashi because
תוספות Tosafos says otherwise. Okay, so תוספות Tosafot says, like Rashi—תוספות Tosafos
is better for the גמרא. All right, so if you say, if
I'm doing it, if Michael here is doing it and I say
"and me," okay, so "and me" if Michael's around, then I'm embarrassed
to say that I'm like ignoring Michael and talking about myself and
I say... yeah, and I said "and me" in front of his
face. ואני. v'Ani. So I wouldn't, so what obviously ואני v'Ani means
in Michael's presence is, and "I'm here for you buddy, I care
for you and if you have a son, I'm also going to
be a נזיר." nazir Meaning that the ואני v'Ani is like "and
if you have a son," not "if I have a son."
Because רש״י Rashi says...
yeah, I know, that's what was confusing me, but that's not what
תוספות Tosafos says. Okay, כסיפא ליה מילתא ksifa lei milta means if
I'm in Michael's presence, I'm embarrassed to ignore Michael. So if Michael
says... it was clearly Michael here wants a son, he's making a
vow to be a נזיר. nazir So in that case when I
say ואני, v'Ani, ואני v'Ani means, maybe עלי Alai would be different,
but at least ואני v'Ani would mean "I'm here for you buddy,
and if you have a son, I'm also going to be a
נזיר." nazir Okay. So if you say that כה באנפי כסיפא ליה
מילתא, k'vei anpei ksifa lei milta, that if you're in the guy's
presence you're embarrassed to ignore him, and obviously you're talking about you're
going to be there for that guy and you're going to be
a נזיר nazir, if he has a son. So אמר הריני נזיר
לכשיהיה לפלוני בן. amar Hareini nosie l'ksheyiheye l'ploni ben.
Now there's a third person. Michael says "I'll be a נזיר nazir
if Charlie's got a son." Now Charlie is not around here, so
I'm not, I don't feel that I have to make any declaration
of loyalty to Charlie, he's not in the room. Okay. So Michael
says "I'll be a נזיר nazir if Charlie has a son" ושמע
חברו ואמר ואני, v'shama chaveiro v'amar v'ani, and I say "me too."
מהו? mahu? מי אמרינן דלאו באנפיה אנפיה קאמר? mi amrinan d'lav b'anpei
anpei ka'amar?
Once Charlie isn't in the room and there's no pressure to make
any claim of loyalty to him, if I say "and me," I
mean "and I'll be a נזיר nazir. if I have a son."
Okay. או דלמא, O dilma, or do we say הכי קאמר ליה,
hachi ka'amar lei, רחמנא ליך כוותיך, rachmana lach kvateich, or maybe we
say you know what, Michael, you've just expressed such a care for
Charlie, so even though I don't have a feeling of a need
to express loyalty to Charlie because he's not in the room, I
maybe have a need to express loyalty to you. I see how
much you care for Charlie. If you care for Charlie that much.
that you're ready to be a נזיר nazir when he has a
son, I, I love you so much Michael and you, you mean
so much to me that I'll, and I see how much you
care for Charlie so I'll also be a נזיר nazir when he
has a son. Okay.
You see what I'm saying?
You're saying you'll be a נזיר nazir
when Charlie has a son.
I see that Michael cares so much for Charlie and for Charlie
to have a son that he's prepared to be a נזיר nazir
if that's what happens for Charlie and I, I care for Michael.
Michael's here. I want to, I feel a pressure to express my
loyalty not to Charlie, but to Michael. So Michael, if you're willing
to dedicate yourself so much, I'm in there with you. I'm going
to also dedicate myself to be a נזיר Nazir if Charlie has
a son.
When I have a son, you could have said.
No, you don't need a son. You've had a lot of kids.
You're not interested in having more kids. Well, that's not the conversation.
So the interesting thing is because the guy, what is fascinating about
this is, right, until now we've had a lot of cases where
the נזירים nezirim walk in in front of you and you say
ואני, ve'ani, like you see this phenomenon and you sort of say
like, "Oh, I want to be like that." But here there's like
a dynamic which, a different type of a dynamic that is going
on which is like, I want to not like you're presenting me
with a model that, "Oh, that's a nice idea, I should try
that for myself." But actually what's happening here and the way that
it's reading, that's in the possibility that I say, "And I'll be
a נזיר Nazir. if I have a son." Oh, you gave me
a great idea. Let me do the same thing for myself. That's
the version of אף נסי כמה. af nesei kama. But the other
version is, that wasn't like a great idea, but because you're saying
that in my presence and I have a relationship with you, I
might feel a need to show that I'm like there for you.
That I'm moved and I have to show a loyalty to you.
So it's not you gave me an idea, but what I'm about
to say is to say that I am actually, you know, not,
not moved and inspired, that was the version that I accepted for
myself. No, because I, because you've said that, you've expressed such a
conviction to this, I feel that it's like there's a pressure on
me to say that, that you know, that I have that sense
of loyalty and concern for you that I'm going to be there
for you and do the same thing to help you out. So
if what you're trying to do is have a son, I'm going
to help you out by committing to be a נזיר Nazir, if
you have a son. If what you care about is that Charlie
has a son, then I want to help you out and I
want to commit to being a נזיר Nazir, if Charlie has a
son because I see you care so much for Charlie. Okay. So
that's a very different type of a dynamic. It's about being with
you because I care for you rather than you inspiring me with
this idea. All right. And by the way, it is interesting, right,
about, well anyway, yes, oh, you did, you wanted to say something.
Yeah.
Would you say anything about the distinction between somebody saying, it's like
saying to השם, Hashem, "If you give me this, then I will
do this for you," and somebody saying, "I just want to do
this with you because I want to do it, not because I
want something in return"?
Right. So I mean, that's what I was actually going to say,
which is that part of the other thing you see in this
dynamic is what תוספות Tosafos has pointed out before, this whole like
deal with God. Now it wasn't said explicitly, but it's a little
implicit. Like, why does it show you care for him because you're
agreeing to be a, why are you saying, "I'll be a נזיר
Nazir if I have a child," if somebody has a child or
whatever? Clearly there's some sense of like, now you could sort of
say like, it's not a deal with God, it's somehow I'll be
so grateful it'll be my thanks to God. But you know, but
there's a thin line between saying I'll express my thanks this way
as like, because I'm promising to express my thanks, I think that
that'll be leverage that God will actually do it. Right. I do
think that that's a subtext here, that there's like a little, you
know, deal, making a deal with God type of a thing. Look,
it goes back to the תורה. Torah. The first נדר neder in
the תורה: Torah: אם יהיה אלהים עמדי ושמרני בדרך הזה אשר אנכי
הולך, im yiheyeh Elokim imadi ushmarani baderech hazeh asher anochi holech, right?
Yeah, that, that seems to be a classic type of a mode.
Yes.
No, it's funny. I mean, I'm just thinking that for all these
cases it may be that this was such a reality that, you
know, that this happened all the time. Like, you know, I'm just
putting this in context, I can see like there's some שמעון or
some יהודה and if all your friends said they'll be a נזיר,
Nazir would you be one too? You know what I mean? Right.
Like that's what it seems like.
True. It's true. Yep. Okay. So let's take a look.
תיבעי, right, תיבעי. I, so Gemara ends with a question mark.
Yeah. תיקו, exactly. Okay, next משנה. mishnah. הריני נזיר, hareini nazir,
I will be a נזיר Nazir, starting
now. ונזיר כשיהיה לי בן. venazir kesheyiheh li ben.
So here David, here's how you prove that your, it's not all
a deal. Okay. You start by saying, "I'm going to be a
נזיר Nazir, right now." Regardless whether God gives me a son or
not, I'm going to be a נזיר. nazir But you know what?
I'll be a נזיר nazir a second time if I have a
child. That makes it, but that makes it a little less, less,
less, all being about a deal, right? Like guy's already a
בעל צדקה, ba'al tzedakah, he's giving $10,000 to charity, you know. So
I have a child, I'll give another $10,000. It's not like it's
all about a deal, right? So that's maybe more framing it as
thankfulness than as about a deal because you're already promising to be
a נזיר nazir. regardless.
He does two נזירים? nezirim?
I don't know. So let's take a look what the משנה mishnah
says. So you say you're going to be a נזיר nazir and
you'll be a נזיר nazir when you have a child. התחיל מונה
את שלו, hischil moneh es shelo, so you start counting the נזירות
Nezirut that you accepted starting today. Okay. ואחר כך נולד לו בן,
v'achar kach nolad lo ben,
and then you had your son a week later, before you finish
finish the נזירות Nezirut, you're in the middle of, you do thirty
days, and then presumably you bring a קרבן, Korban, you end your
first נזירות. Nezirut Once your first נזירות Nezirut. ends, then the one
of your son which is hovering and hasn't taken effect yet because
the first one took effect first, so this one can't take effect
on top of it. So once you finish your first נזירות Nezirut
by bringing a קרבן, korban then the second one will kick in
and take effect.
You do another sixty
days as the ones that are... Right, except just wait a minute.
Okay,
so... Now let's say you said, הריני נזיר שיהיה לי בן ונזיר.
Hareini Nazir she'yiheyeh li ben venazir.
In reverse order. I'll be a נזיר nazir when I have a
son and I'm a נזיר. nazir Now if you said and am
a נזיר, nazir. that will take place after the first נזירות, Nezirut
then fine, you would just wait till you had a son and
then you do one and then you do the second one. But
actually since you just said and a נזיר, nazir even though it
was your second statement, since you didn't say the time, you mean
and a נזיר nazir now. So you're in an interesting situation in
which your נזירות Nezirut starts now, but it's conceptually the second נזירות.
Nezirut You right now are starting to practice your second נזירות Nezirut.
before your first נזירות Nezirut, because your first נזירות Nezirut. hasn't taken
effect yet. So that's going to get interesting once your first נזירות
Nezirut. comes on the scene because you're you're in you're doing it
now but what you're doing now is your second נזירות. Nezirut Okay.
ונזיר. Venazir. התחיל מונה שלו. He'chil moneh shelo. So right now you
start your second one. Okay, ואחר כך נולד לו בן, Va'achar kach
nolad lo ben, then you have the son. So now your first
נזירות, Nezirut, it's time to do your first נזירות. Nezirut מניח את
שלו ומונה של בנו. Maniach et shelo umoneh shel beno. Now because
your first is your first, that has to take precedence. You have
to put your second one aside, I'll tell you in a minute,
pause your second one, practice your first one, okay, ואחר כך משלים
את שלו. Ve'achar kach mashlim et shelo. Then after you do the
thirty days for your son, you go back and you make up
however many days. So you did ten days, your son was born,
so then it's okay, it's time the first one takes precedence over
the second. And now I do thirty days for my son, then
I go back and I do twenty days for number one. Now,
excellent question. Do I bring קרבנות Korbanot and do I shave? So
the משנה Mishnah is very vague on all of this. תוספות Tosafos
basically says that it's impossible, I mean the גמרא says implicit about
this but it's all very vague in the משנה, Mishnah, it's impossible
that you would actually go ahead and shave at the end of
the first one because then how could you just do twenty days?
Twenty days is not enough for נזירות. Nezirut. Now you could say
well maybe you would do a full thirty days afterwards, but that's
not what the משנה Mishnah says. The משנה Mishnah says you're משלים.
Mashlim. So how so if you're only going to do twenty days
after, you cannot have shaved at the end of the בן ben
one, at the end of the son one, so
those ten days just suspended.
Yes. So if it was just counting credits towards days and numbers
you could, but since part of the need of thirty days is
so it's considered to be גידול פרע Giddel pera and you can't
end your נזירות Nezirut, without having achieved גידול פרע Giddel pera and
so on, which raises interesting questions for bald people accepting נזירות, neziros.
I understand. But anyway, but there's this assumption that you can't, I
know, there is this assumption that you cannot shave and then end
your נזירות neziros. without being less than thirty days since you shaved.
So since the משנה Mishnah makes it clear that you only need
twenty days after the one of the בן, ben. so saying according
to this approach, basically there's going to be no shaving until you're
done with both and it becomes very bizarre because what it allows
you to say is you get off the hook of having to
do two sets of קרבנות, Korbanot, right? You basically accepted two נזירות.
neziros, Normally when you accept two נזירות, neziros one you know one
has to end. If I basically say I'm a נזיר nazir and
a נזיר, nazir the second one only kicks in after the first,
not after thirty days. If I'm lapping it out and waiting to
go to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and it's two years since
since I've been a נזיר, the second one only kicks in after
I finish the first one, even two years later. You need the
first one to end before the second one kicks in. That's normally
the logic. Here because there was this weird setup that you did
the second one before the first, and then it became time for
the first, and if you were now to go ahead and to
shave or whatever you wouldn't be able you'd have to start all
over again, somehow there's this idea that you get to do them
both without you get to do the first without ending the second.
Okay, if the logical order was first and then second, second can't
begin until first is over, until you bring the קרבנות. Korbanot. But
since you did second and then first, you started with the second,
so
then the first
can begin when it's time for first. Who cares that second didn't
end? One doesn't need two to end. One is first. Okay, so
therefore you're allowed to begin one without ending two. And then because
two you've already started two, you're allowed to to complete two without
having ended one. So what you wind up being able to do
is you do a straight sixty days and you bring the קרבן
korban at the end. I don't know, it's not
going to be any זמן קטן zman katan anymore, it's day 40,
right?
Oh don't let's not worry with math yet. Let's try to figure
this out. Okay? So that's what the משנה Mishna says: מונה של
בנו ואחר כך משלים את שלו. Moneh shel bno v'achar kach mashlim
et shelo. Now, if that weren't confusing enough, okay, I'm going to
read ahead because in order to understand the גמרא and the reason
we have all these תוספות Tosafot in this case, because תוספות really
explains the next משנה. Mishna. So let's read ahead to the next
משנה Mishna just to give you the full picture and then we'll
flip back. Look at the משנה Mishna on ט"ו עמוד א' Tes
Vav Amud Aleph and here's what the משנה Mishna says.
ט"ו. Tes Vav.
הריני נזיר לכשיהיה לי בן ונזיר מהיום. Hareini nazir l'ksheyehiyeh li ben
v'nazir mei'hayom. I'll be a נזיר when I have a בן ben
and I'm a נזיר starting now for a hundred days. Okay, similar
to our scenario except you're a hundred-day נזיר. Okay. So you start
with your number two נזירות. neziros, Okay. You start with your number
two נזירות. neziros Your number two
נזירות, neziros okay. Your number two נזירות nezirut because you said the
order you said is I'll be a נזיר when I have a
בן ben and then or and a נזיר hundred days. So because
you didn't have a בן ben yet you started with your number
two נזירות, nezirut? okay. And then you had a בן ben somewhere
here. Okay, then you had a בן. ben And so now let's
take a look and your בן ben is going to then's the
one you're going to do your number one נזירות nezirut. of thirty
days. How many days have you done of your number two נזירות
nezirut, of a hundred days? Okay. נולד
לו בן עד שבעים לא הפסיד כלום. Nolad lo ben ad shivim
lo hifsid klum. Up till seventy days you didn't lose anything. Why?
Because seventy days means you'll have at least thirty days left afterwards.
You have thirty days left afterwards so what you get to do
here is because you have thirty days afterwards, this the one of
the בן ben will here's your virtual hundred days, okay? The virtual
hundred days goes like this, right? And but you had your בן
ben. that's the whole hundred, okay? If your בן ben, is born
somewhere in there so by the time the thirty days of the
בן is over you're not yet out of number two, you're still
within the hundred days of number
two, you get to double dip. You get to basically say: Okay,
I shifted to number one. Now when number one is over I'm
still in the time frame of number two so I can also
consider it like I've been doing number two all along. And I
don't have to do and I can do a hundred days for
both of them. I don't have to wind up doing a hundred
thirty days.
What if he's born on day 71? But if the kid was
born there so I have to shift gears and do this, okay?
And now I've done how
many you done?
80 days. If he was born 80... Say 80.
Okay, day 80. And then it's like this. Okay, so then that
gets me outside. So then what does it say? Then it says:
לאחר שבעים סותר... Le'achar shivim soter... now the language in our משנה
Mishna is סותר שבעים, soter shivim, תוספות takes out the word שבעים
shivim and just says סותר soter שאין תגלחת פחות משלושים יום. she'ein
tiglachas pachus mishloshim yom. Basically
what happens here is because this puts me outside, right? It's considered
like okay I can't double dip because now I'm outside of my
first hundred. I can't say I'm still in number two. I'm not
still in number two. I gotta finish number two. And since I
gotta finish number two, I can't finish number two with only twenty
days because שאין תגלחת פחות משלושים יום, ein tiglachas pachus mishloshim yom,
so I gotta like finish number two with like another thirty days.
You said סותר, soter, though.
סותר soter means... No, סותר soter doesn't mean like knocks
out
everything although that's what it sounds like. I know. But if the
סותר זמן soter zman is twenty, don't count twenty or whatever. You
have to do a full thirty.
Right. So there's a question though because it's not so פשוט. pashut.
It might mean that it's סותר soter that I don't get to
double dip and maybe I only have to do another twenty not
another thirty. That's all the fun we'll figure out when we get
to that משנה. Mishna. So I don't know why I felt necessary
to look at this משנה Mishna now because תוספות looks at it,
but just to make us appreciate that our case is there are
cases where there are three scenarios. Okay? Here are the three models.
Right? Model number one is you basically have the case of
you
first do number one and then right and then you bring a
you say הריני נזיר ולכשיהיה לי בן. Hareini nazir v'liksheyehiyeh li ben.
So you the one you started with is your number one. Okay,
then you finish that and then you bring a קרבן korban and
then you do your number two. The case of נזיר that's easy:
נזיר ונזיר לכשיהיה לי בן.
Nazir
v'nazir ksheyiye li ben.
לכשיהיה לי בן Ksheyiye li ben
is one after the first thirty.
So well no the בן could be born here, it doesn't matter
when the בן is born but since you were doing number one,
it doesn't get preempted. That's the easy one. The other case, the
more interesting cases, is when you said is when you said נזיר
לכשיהיה nazir lekeshiye right ונזיר. venazir. So נזיר
when I have a son and a נזיר. So since you didn't
say נזיר then and a נזיר now, you start it now, but
what you're starting now is number two. And that's interesting because it
allows it to be preempted. Okay, so in that case, you start
with number two. Here's your בן. Once you have your בן, that
preempts. And then you do your thirty days, and then you're going
to, let's say this was like twenty days, and then you're going
to be משלים mashlim another ten. And because, and now you could
have said you'll have to do a whole new thirty, but because
we are somehow saying that on the one hand, you didn't have
to bring a קרבן korban, here, okay, here there's a קרבן, korban,
here there's no קרבן, korban, because since here it's number one, number
one gets to preempt and say you didn't need number two to
finish for number one, number one is number one. It gets to
start when it's ready to start. Okay. So you did number one
without a קרבן, korban and because somehow you were entitled to start
the first twenty, we somehow, we're not going to make you do
more, you know, all we're going to demand is that you finish
it. So you don't bring a קרבן korban here either, because then
you'd have to start the whole thing again. So therefore you don't
bring a קרבן korban here, you don't bring a קרבן korban here,
and you get to just do ten more and then you're done.
And then the other, and then that's scenario number two, which is
just משלים. mashlim. And then category number three is when you actually
are, what do you call it? When you actually are not משלים
mashlim but you double dip. And when you double dip, right, that's
when you basically accepted a hundred days, right?
I shouldn't have used different, double dipping.
Yeah, I don't know the terminology. You started with your number two,
it's a hundred days, okay. And then your number one comes here.
In that case, you don't even have to be משלים, mashlim, right?
Your, this was sixty, thirty, ten. You don't even have to be
משלים. mashlim. Right here was on pause, because but here if the
thing ends within the framework of it, you get to double dip.
So those three scenarios.
Scenario that you drew originally. Oh, yeah, eighty. Yeah, yeah, I have
a question. I know,
but it's not our משנה. mishna. So could we just hold off
on that? Yes.
My question is, I wasn't sure how that relates to because his
hair is already long at eighty. Right. So you said something about
his hair, he doesn't have the time for his hair to be
long enough. Which one, the hair for the thirty or for the
eighty? Follow you?
Yeah, I do. But can we wait till we do that, till
we get to that משנה? mishna? Alright, let's take a look at
our גמרא.
Where the משנה mishna says double dipping is לא השלים כלום. lo
hishlim klum.
Thank you, there you go. Okay, בשני פרקים bishnei perakim
you're allowed to double dip. Let's take a look at our גמרא,
okay. So maybe I shouldn't have jumped us ahead there, but it
was now we see the scope of it. Couldn't do this. בעי
רבא. baei rava. We now have six minutes left. רבא rava
asked, אמר הריני נזיר לאחר עשרים יום ומעכשיו מאה יום. amar hareini
nazir le'achar esrim yom ume'achshav me'ah yom. Now let's say the guy
explicitly identified, here the point was things were taking effect, but you
weren't in control of when they would take effect. You were prepared
for having everything taking place now. Let's say you very specifically post-dated
it, right? You specifically identified when it would start taking effect. You
said, because when you say לכשיהיה לי בן, lekeshiye li ben, you
don't know when that's going to be. So you say הריני נזיר
לאחר עשרים יום, hareini nazir le'achar esrim yom, I'll be a נזיר
in twenty days, ומעכשיו מאה יום, ume'achshav me'ah yom, and starting now
a hundred days. מהו? mahu. What do we say? כיון דהני מאה
בעשרין לא שלמי, keivan dehani me'ah be'esrin lo shalmi, so since those
hundred days are not, do not end by the time you get
to the twenty days, לא חיילין, lo chayilin, they shouldn't take effect
at all? או דילמא כיון דאית ליה גידול שיער לבסוף שפיר דמי,
o dilma keivan de'it lei gidul sei'ar levasof shapir dami, getting to
the point, since there'll at least be the growing of the hair
after, חיילין, chayilin, it takes place. So basically what's the case? The
case is you say, I'm going to be a נזיר after twenty
days. Here's your day one, here's your day twenty. You've identified the
standard נזירות nezirut? after twenty days, okay. We'll call it number one
because it's the first thing you did. הריני נזיר לאחר hareini nazir
le'achar and you said and I'm going to be a נזיר מאה
יום. nazir me'ah yom. So you're not going to, if you were
to start now, you would not be right, it would not be
over by the time the first one was over. Maybe if it
would be over, maybe if this one were to start after ninety
days or so, or after
seventy, right, here you'll still have something left to be done after.
So
I don't know, hold on, I'm confusing myself. Let's one more time.
Let's take כיון דאית ליה גידול שיער לבסוף, keivan de'it lei gidul
sei'ar levasof, מהו. כיון דהני מאה בעשרין לא שלמי לא חיילין. keivan
dehani me'ah be'esrin lo shalmi lo chayilin. Ah, since I won't be
done, if I were to start now, I'm not going to get
a chance to be done by the time this is over, right?
So since I'm not going to get a chance to be done,
why start now if I can't finish it? Sort of the idea.
Since I'm not going to get a chance to be done. Not
going to be able to finish it, and I'm going to have
to do days afterwards, okay, maybe we shouldn't even get started now,
and we should just get started over here, okay, after twenty, fifty
days later. Right. Don't start it now if you can't finish it.
What do we say? No, start it now, you'll have this and
you know what? Even afterwards, when you have to finish it afterwards,
you're still going to have the opportunity to grow your hair because
there's still going to be like another fifty days or so to
do. I mean, there's an interesting question whether that gets, that presumably,
you know, would be included in the hundred, would you double-dip here?
Okay. But since there'll be an opportunity to still do the גידול
שיער gidul se'ar after, maybe you actually should be able to, you
know, start now and then you'll make it up. Now the question
is, the only reason we, right, the reason that we mention גידול
שיער gidul se'ar suggests, that's why so many key points is missing
from this discussion. The fact that we've mentioned גידול שיער gidul se'ar
suggests that you're bringing a קרבן korban, here. Okay. Right. So and
you say, well, maybe I should start, and even though I'm going
to have to bring a קרבן, korban, and that will mean that
I'll have to cut my hair, but since there'll be time to
regrow the hair, maybe I should start now and be able to
at least count like those twenty days. Okay, now how does it
exactly fit here? Here I don't have to bring a קרבן, korban,
here I do have to bring a קרבן, korban you know, that's
sort of like תוספות tries to figure out. Somehow the fact that
here I am directly manipulating when everything is going to take effect
means that I am like, I am more, if here the reason
like I didn't bring the קרבן was because like, like I had
to stop this and move to number one, because number one was
number one and therefore, you know, it gets priority. But here I'm
arranging the whole thing from the very beginning. Like I know exactly
the way it's going to lay out at the beginning. It's not
out of my hands, it's not when am I going to have
a child? And since I'm somehow laying it out, like you know,
then that
sort of requires that like when one is over you stop that
to begin the next one. And we'll say the same thing presumably
to a birth that's very imminent, about to give birth any day,
you say it'll only, maybe. All right, let's just read, I don't
know, let's just read the next line of the גמרא. Okay. ותיבעי
ליה נזירות מועטת. v'tibei lei nezirut mu'etat. Why did he have to
ask by a hundred-day נזירות? nezirut, Ask about a small נזירות. nezirut,
Okay, meaning what would be if you would just say a hundred-day
נזירות, nezirut, what if you would just say a thirty-day נזירות? nezirut
Do we say don't get started if you can't finish, or do
we say start it, do this, and then finish it? So the
גמרא says חדא מיגו חדא קמיבעיא ליה. chada migu chada kamibaya lei.
Yeah, one question is built on the next question. אם תימצי לומר
נזירות מועטת, im timtzi lomar nezirut mu'etat, if you say a small
נזירות, nezirut. כיון דעשרה יומין הוא דיתירן, keivan d'asara yomin hu d'yasiran,
there's only going to be ten days left. לא סליק להו הלין
עשרה. lo salik lehu hanin asara. So, so that these, so that
you're not going to have the next, wait, these, no, the twenty
days left. עשרה יומין הוא דיתירן. asara yomin hu d'yasiran. So you
first did twenty days. Right. So since you first did twenty days,
these last ten are not going to count by themselves. And since
they're not going to count by themselves, you don't want to get
the whole thing started all together. So עשרה יומין הוא דיתירן לא
סליק להו הלין עשרה, asara yomin hu d'yasiran lo salik lehu hanin
asara, then בר נזיר מאה יום, bar nazir me'ah yom, כיון דאיתיה
תמנין יומין לבסוף, keivan d'isya tmanin yomin l'vasof, סליק ליה. salik lei.
So what would we say if you said I'm going to do
a standard נזירות, nezirut, okay, and we were to say in a
case of a standard נזירות, we would say ah, what would be
the case if you said a standard נזירות but you preset the
days they took effect? What would we say if you did that,
then this case you certainly wouldn't get started. Because if you get
started here you only have ten days left at the end and
that's not enough and therefore it's not worth getting started. Fine, that
might not be worth getting started because you're only going to have
ten days here at the end and that's not going to be
enough for a full נזירות. But maybe if you did a hundred
days, that would be worth getting started because then you would have
a significant thing standing by itself at the end. Okay. Is that
clear? Yeah. All right. So do we say מאה יום, me'ah yom,
but maybe נזיר מאה יום, nazir me'ah yom, כיון דאיתיה תמנין יומין
לבסוף, keivan d'isya tmanin yomin l'vasof, for a hundred-day נזירות, that is
worth getting started, סליק ליה. salik lei. Then then actually it would
go for you because then you would want to, you know, you'll
get started and you'll have enough afterwards. או לא, or do we
not say that? What? It's more... ואם תימצי לומר. v'im timtzi lomar.
I know. ואם תימצי לומר חיילי, v'im timtzi lomar chaili, אמר הריני
נזיר. amar hareni nazir. No, but that's going to be what we'll
do tomorrow. That's a new question. All right, getting a little confusing.
Now it's all left for Shabbos where we won't have use of
the board. Okay, just playing with prepare the board means that we're
finished.